so let's talk about magnetic discs which
today usually means a hard dis or a hard
drive but the so-called floppy discs are
also magnetic discs and work very much
along the same lines it's just that
today we mostly have hard drives and few
people even remember floppy drives a
magnetic disc has a spindle to which we
can attach so-called platters all of the
platters are attached to the same
spindle and rotate at the same speed
let's say in this direction there is a
motor here that really drives the
spindle to rotate and that causes all
the platters to rotate at the same speed
if we look at a single platter it has a
surface covered with Magnetic material
on one side and also on another so a dis
drive that has three platters usually
will have a total of six surfaces the
data bits are on all the surfaces we
access this data by having a magnetic
head attached to an arm and another one
for the lower surface and then all of
these heads are attached to a head
assembly which can move all the heads in
unison so if this head is here this head
will be in the same position on another
platter and so on we don't individually
move the heads we move them all at the
same time so because the platter is
rotating and the head is staying in
place usually the head will be able to
access this circle on the surface of the
disc each head will be able to access
the circle on its own surface and all of
these are going to be at the same
distance from the spindle this is called
a track all of the tracks at the same
distance from the spindle form what is
called a cylinder the cylinder simply
consists of one track from each
surface where the tracks in the
cylinders are those that can be accessed
by different heads at the same time so
for example here there are six heads
when they stay in this position and all
the plats rotate they're able to access
the six tracks of that cylinder the way
we access different tracks on the disc
is by moving the head so that it comes
closer or gets further from the spindle
and that way we can access the entire
area of each surface so the data
naturally will be organized into bits
that are positioned along the track and
then another track will have different
bits and so on if we look at the surface
from above and this is now the spindle
this would be one track and this would
be another and finally on one track we
don't store data continuously through
the track because usually a lot of bits
are on a single track instead the data
along one track is divided into sectors
and a sector will be the smallest unit
that we can actually read now if the
disc rotates in this direction and the
head is currently here as the disc
rotates different bits of the sector are
going to be under the head so the sector
will have some Preamble here that is a
recognizable bit pattern that tells the
head that this is the beginning of a
sector then we have the appropriate
number of the bits for the sector that
actually hold the data followed usually
by some check sum and other information
that is needed to possibly correct
errors in this sector and then another
sector will just have the same things
and so on so when the head assembly
moves to a particular cylinder then the
heads start listening for the beginning
of the sector once they see the
beginning of the sector and see which
sector it is they know where they are in
the whole track so the disc capacity can
be computed as the number of platters
time two this would really be the number
of surfaces times how many tracks we
have per surface or expressed in another
way how many cylinders do we have on
these discs times how many sectors do we
have per track times how many bytes of
data do we have in each sector usually
we have a small number of platters such
as 1 2 3 maybe four we have thousands of
tracks per surface tens to hundreds
sectors per track and something like a
kilobyte or maybe half a kilobyte of
bytes per sector so sectors are usually
like kilobyte is in size we have about
100 let's say sectors per track maybe a
little bit more and we have thousands of
tracks per surface obviously the whole
thing needs to be very thin so these
platters are really close to each other
it needs to be let's say 2 and 1/2 in
wide total including the head assembly
and so on so the platters are only a
couple of inches in diameter and because
we have so many tracks per
surface that means that the tracks are
spaced very very close to each other and
the head assembly needs to be very very
precise in how it positions heads